A Guide to the Hundley Family Papers, 1817-1895
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Hundley Family Papers, 1817-1995
The Library of Virginia
50051
2.475 cu. ft. and 6 boxes
Hundley family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Margaret Hundley Davis of Center Cross, Virginia.
Alternative Form Available
Collection is available on Miscellaneous microfilm reels 6097-6102.
Biographical Information
The Hundley family was a prominent Essex County, Virginia, family. Larkin Hundley (1795-1872) married Sophronia Evans (d. 1820) 1 March 1819 and they had one son. After his first wife's death, Hundley married Eliza B. Whiting (1798-1853) on 27 November 1822, and they had seven children, only two of which reached adulthood. One son, James Hervey Hundley (1830-1903) married Sophronia Dyke (1832-1927) 12 January 1853 and they had ten children, including Peyton Hundley (1865-1942) who married Frances Williams Baxley (1876-1961) and Lucy Temple Hundley (1871-1970) who married John F. Anderson (1871-1958). Peyton Hundley's son Peyton Hundley, Jr., (1907-1993) married Idell Baker (1920-2009) and they had five children.
Louis Kuindz was born in Germany 28 July 1828. He emigrated to the United States and eventually settled in Essex County, Virginia. Kuindz was a carpenter and builder who worked on Rose Hill and other homes and buildings in Essex County. He died in Essex County 31 August 1870 and was buried in the Rose Hill Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1817-1995, of the Hundley family of Essex County, Virginia, consisting of correspondence, deeds, estate papers, financial papers, genealogical notes and charts, guardianship papers, legal papers, plats, sermons, surveys, wills, and other papers regarding the Hundley family and its home Rose Hill. Collection also includes the papers of Louis Kuindz of Essex County, including correspondence, receipts, naturalization papers, books, and other papers.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Letters, 1817-1995.
Series II: Deeds, Plats, and Surveys, 1790-1923.
Series III: Wills, Estate Papers, and Guardianship Papers, 1687-1962.
Series IV: Legal and Financial Papers, 1821-1944.
Series V: Subject files.
Series VI: Genealogy.
Series VII: Sermons.
Series VIII: Louis Kuindz Papers, 1857-1870.
Contents List
- Series I: Letters, 1817-1995., Extent: 1 box. (Box 1)
  Letters, 1817-1995, mainly concerning the Hundley family of Rose Hill in Essex County and containing most correspondence of Larkin Hundley, Eliza B. Whiting Hundley, and James Hervey Hundley. Letters discuss Larkin Hundley's and Eliza Whiting's courtship; Larkin Hundley's guardianship of the Dyke family children; applications for the position of teacher at a proposed school at Rose Hill; James Hervey Hundley's education at Fleetwood Academy and Washington College; and James Hervey Hundley's ordination as an Episcopal priest and his honorary degree from Washington and Lee University. Also includes Lucy Hundley's (Anderson's) education and honeymoon in England and France; life of a Virginia Military Institute cadet during the Civil War; Essex County and Richmond, Virginia, during the Civil War; and family and local news. 20th century correspondence mostly concerns genealogical information on the Hundley and related families, but also includes an invitation for John F. and Lucy Hundley Anderson to dine at the White House with Woodrow Wilson (1856-1924) and a wedding invitation. Also contains envelopes.
  Chronological
  - Letters, 1817-1818. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1822. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1831, 1838-1839, [183-]. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1840-1847. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1848-1849. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1850-1858. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1861-1869. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1871-1876. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1882-1899. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1900-1928. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1932-1939. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1943-1968. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters, 1975-1995, no date [20th century]. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Envelopes. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II: Deeds, Plats, and Surveys, 1790-1923., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  Deeds, Plats, and Surveys, 1790-1923, contain deeds, 1821-1923, for real property in Norfolk and Essex and King and Queen Counties, Virginia; personal property in Essex and Middlesex Counties, Virginia; and for slaves. Papers also contain plats and surveys, 1790-1851, 1901, for property in Essex County and for oyster grounds in the Rappahannock River.
  - Deeds, 1821-1863. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Deeds, 1882-1923. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Plats and Surveys, 1790-1851, 1901, no date. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series III: Wills, Estate Papers, and Guardianship Papers, 1687-1962., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  Wills, Estate Papers, and Guardianship Papers, 1687-1962, contain the wills, 1687-1901, of James Dyke (1786-1853), Peyton Hundley (1865-1942), Josiah McTyre (d. 1795), and Robert Smith (d. ca. 1687); Estate papers, 1815-1962, contains estate papers of Claude Baxley (1838-1918), Edwin Hundley (1801-1837), Frances Baxley Hundley (1876-1961), Maria Hundley (d. ca. 1875), Peyton Hundley, and Thomas Hundley (1757-1814); and guardianship papers, 1833-1845, of Larkin Hundley (1795-1872) for Catherine, Susan, and William A. Dyke.
  - Wills, 1687, 1795, 1853, 1901. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Claude Baxley Estate Papers, 1918-1919. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Edwin Hundley Estate Papers, 1837-1844. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Frances B. Hundley Estate Papers, 1943-1962. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Thomas Hundley, Maria Hundley and Peyton Hundle Estate Papers, 1815, 1876, 1943. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Guardianship Papers of Larkin Hundley for Catherine, Susan and William A. Dyke, 1833-1845. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Legal and Financial Papers, 1821-1944., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  Legal and Financial Papers, 1821-1944, contains Accounts, 1821-1924, of John W. Roy with Kemp Evans, 1821-1823; Larkin Hundley with Oliver White for sons' board and tuition at Fleetwood Academy, 1838, 1845-1846; Larkin Hundley with John W. Robinson, 1847; Mary Bohannon with her trustee Larkin Hundley, 1851-1855; J. G. Gannon with George A. Hundley merchant for groceries, 1883; Peyton Hundley with George L. Smith and Brother for oysters and other items, 1923-1924. Also contains receipts, 1838-1863, for tuition at Fleetwood Academy, interest in a steam boat, church subscription, slaves, newspapers, and shipping receipts. Also taxes, 1864, paid in kind by James Hervey Hundley and taxes, 1942-1944, paid by Frances B. Hundley; bonds payable, 1832-1847, mainly of Larkin Hundley; commission, 8 December 1829, for Larkin Hundley as militia captain; announcement, 2 June 1823, of trustee sale; minister's bond, 1858, for James Hervey Hundley as minister of Union Baptist Church; power of attorney, 15 November 1831, to Larkin Hundley; summons, 5 January 1842, for Royston Betts and Richard Matlack[?], merchants; announcement of chancery suit, Larkin Hundley vs. Thomas Pitts' executor, et al; valuation of property; Richmond Agency of New York Life Insurance Company; and letterhead stationery for Hundley and Son general merchandise.
  - Accounts, 1821-1924. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Receipts, 1838-1863, 1890. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Taxes, 1864, 1942-1944. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bonds Payable, 1832-1847. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Financial and Legal Miscellaneous Papers, 1823-1858, no date. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series V: Subject files., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  Subject files contains information on Rose Hill in Essex County including insurance report, list of slaves, and tour presentations; Rose Hill cemetery records; photographs of Rose Hill and persons; and Rose Hill School. Also contains calling cards from the Hundley family of Colnbrook in Essex County; minutes and constitution of the Jolly club, a debating and social club; information on South Farnham Parish, St. Anne's Glebe, and St. Luke's Church; reports and receipts of the Essex County Board of Supervisors and Overseers of the Poor; reports and clippings on Essex County; and miscellaneous papers, including poems.
  - Rose Hill. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rose Hill cemetery records, also Tom Evans' place. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Rose Hill photographs, also individuals. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Rose Hill School. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Colnbrook. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - The Jolly Club--debating society and social club. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Episcopal Church--South Farnham Parish, St. Anne's Glebe, and St. Luke's Church. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Essex County--Board of Supervisors, Overseers of the Poor, essay, and clippings. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous Papers. (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Series VI: Genealogy., Extent: 1 box. (Box 3)
  Genealogy contains Hundley family Bible records and genealogical research on the following families: Hundley, Anderson, Baxley, Beverley, Buckner, Corbin, Dyke, Farinholt, Frost, Hill, Hoskins, Kingsley, Muse, Peachey, Powell, Pratt, Robinson, Roy, Smith, Whiting, Williams, and Wormley. Also includes lineage charts and papers for membership in the Colonial Dames of America.
  - Hundley Family Bible Records. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hundley book by Lucy Temple Hundley Anderson. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Hundleys of Rose Hill by Elizabeth Peyton Hundley. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Hundleys of Rose Hill by Elizabeth Peyton Hundley--research notebook. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Name and Family of Hundley by Media Research Bureau. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Hundley family (folder 1 of 3). (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hundley family (folder 2 of 3). (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Hundley family (folder 3 of 3). (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sketch of James Hervey Hundley. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - James Hervey Hundley and Sophronia James Hundley clippings. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Peyton Hundley. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Anderson family. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Baxley family. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Beverley family. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Buckner family. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Corbin family. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Dyke family. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Farinholt family. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Frost family. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Hill family. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Hoskins family. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Kingsley family. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Muse family. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Peachey family. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Powell family. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Pratt family. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Robinson family. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Roy family. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Whiting family. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Williams family. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Lineage papers--Hundley, Roy, Beverley, Smith, Wormley. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Colonial Dames of America. (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Sermons of James Hervey Hundley., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 4-5)
  Sermons of James Hervey Hundley delivered at Episcopal churches between 1872 and 1901. Includes Biblical text, sermon, notations on when and where delivered, and sermons notes. Also contains newspapers and clippings including issues of The Churchman, The Virginia Churchman, Our Diocesan Work, Our Mountain Work in the Diocese of Virginia, University of Virginia Newsletter, and Family Physician. Also contains list of sermons, date delivered, and location.
  - Sermon data on when and where delivered. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sermons, 1-6. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sermons, 7-12. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sermons, 13-18. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sermons, 19-24. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Sermons, 25-30. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Sermons, 31-36. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Sermons, 37-42. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Sermons, 43-48. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Sermons, 49-54. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Sermons, 55-60. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sermons, 61-66. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sermons, 66-72. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sermons, 73-79. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Sermons notes. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Religous pamphlets. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Religious journals--The Churchman, The Virginia Churchman, and Our Mountain Work in the Diocese of Virginia. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Clippings--Our Diocesan Work, University of Virginia Newsletter, and Family Physician; also cites to other material. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series VIII: Louis Kuindz Papers, 1857-1870., Extent: 1 box. (Box 6)
  Louis Kuindz Papers, 1857-1870, contain the papers of Kuindz (1828-1870) who was a carpenter and builder, including correspondence, receipts, naturalization order, and miscellaneous papers. Much of the correspondence is in German. Also contains three volumes written in German, including a New Testament.
  - Correspondence, 1857, 1868, 1870. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Receipts, 1857-1869. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Wallet. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous papers. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - New Testament in German (volume not located on microfilm). (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Books (in German)--Allgemeine Vorschriften der Unabhängigen Ordens der Rothmänner and a second work missing its title page. (Box 6, Folder 6)